what did you mind so I was thinking the
last old river in turning telling your
world upside down we're gonna die as a
patoot you know thoughts himself to turn
O'Brien upside down v aggregates and and
you were saying in order to do that you
cannot deny just turning turning the
self and the aggregates round
it's not about denying mmm it's not
about just I'm not acting out a bit not
denying but allowing it to endure and
recognizing it and and you say I think
you sort of suggested that kind of if
that's the most difficult thing for a
patina to do but there are you know
certain characteristics of that sense of
self are the most difficulties to see to
see a sense of self yet to seem to pick
up on okay that's what yourself see
there's a phenomenon of think didn't use
my sense of self is such a sensual even
if you can't define it that is its its
characteristic yeah you cannot be
defined but it's really such as an
undefinable ambiguous thing because if
there is absolutely no sense of
whatsoever you talk about yeah
so yes yeah so you can I just say if
petitioner learns how to see the sense
of self he can then eventually see the
right order of the aggregates through
that sense of self not in response to
not as a as a as a means of dealing with
the self but literally just through the
sense of self you see the basis upon
which that sense of self defense and
that basis is not in your control so
seeing the basis is impermanent seeing
the basis suffering means the
experiences that not my self and
alternatively I suppose learning how to
see two simultaneous things means you
can know the other so learning what the
knowledge is yeah it's also a way in the
same direction yeah because when we talk
about two simultaneous things I bet many
people would think like also I have to
think of two things at the same time you
know let balance the extent of them know
as literally now what we are speaking
the body is enduring oh but I didn't
think about it exactly but you know it
so rediscovering Reedus earning that
which already know that it's they're
enduring simultaneously with other
things you're attending to that's that's
how you create the basis for discerning
that sense of self the characteristics
of the sense of self are something you
can attend to on the basis of an
enduring sense of self yeah but if you
have absolutely no no grasp of such a
phonological principle there's nothing
good to see cuz all you see is what you
can put in front of here
yeah and that's where people struggle
like understanding the sense of self
because for them understanding means
being able to put my finger on it yeah
that's all I understanding yeah that's
you attending to it that's you informing
yourself collecting data yeah but none
of that is on the level of understanding
which is always better for all to it so
understanding is being something that
you're not
you cut you're not pretending that
you're not yeah
it's a definition of an insight as well
well like say wouldn't like fully
understanding something when you well
you know they committed any problem you
try to understand problem yeah you're
attending to the to the components yeah
things that constitute your problem you
collect the information about it yeah
but that's not understanding and you
know that that's not understanding and
you can have a lot of information and
you can even make sense out of it to
some extent but still you know it's not
understood cuz the problem is still
there now I imagine while you're making
that effort to figure out all this
information about the problem and then
you get it you wouldn't get it if you
haven't been attending to these things
there's a problem as something that
needs to be understood but you certainly
did not get it simply by attending to
these things mechanically you got it cuz
you understood it so that's I mean it's
all wrong so you can't do you can't do
understanding directly but if you attend
to the right things rightly and know
what you're supposed to understand
that's how you you're closer to getting
understand but you you know you
understand that when you don't need to
do anything about of course once it's
understood it's understood you can
question that understanding you can try
and sort of put it to test so to speak
like revisit it maybe see if it really
holds the water in every regard but yeah
to some degree you understood that so am
i free of suffering when I kind of my
understanding well I'm not sure well
maybe I haven't understood enough having
calculated what I did understand having
because that's the measure it's not like
that you think you understood it's when
you can't suffer anymore you want to
contribute understanding it because of
your understanding your freedom so for
as long as that's not developed you have
to keep pushing that same understanding
same as we started a sense of self
you're not understanding the ambiguity
of the center self and you will not
understand them we go to the sensor for
as long as you think that understanding
is on the level of clarifying
information about the ambiguity it's not
only to some extent you need to know
what you're supposed to understand but
for most people understanding as I said
it's more like when you can define
things have it on your own terms put
your finger on it then it's regarded as
if it's understood because look it's so
clear I've broken down I systematized
systematize all this information about
sense itself in all these charts and
stuff assets so now I just need to get
it and I got it all laid out I memorized
it and it's understood no and the more
you think that that's understanding the
less likely you'll be able to actually
understand them because you're going in
the opposite direction of understanding
you collect the information about it but
do you think it's worth
like considering what the various kind
of characteristics in the sense of
cellphone in itself it's meaningless
doing that if you know why you're doing
it
mmm cuz you want to get understanding
then yes oh yeah so tell me in the view
behind the motivation behind determines
it whether it's helpful or not not oh
just do this blindly and it will be
helpful for you yeah the only thing you
can do blindly they will be helpful for
you is keep the pset yeah just do that
but everything else it depends while
you're doing it and to what extent so
sometimes people will be ok so I'll just
attend to the characteristic of this and
stuff because they're trying to get rid
of the discomfort yeah you know you're
understanding you're just using it to
acting out of same type of craving so
you won't understand the nature of it
what is the nature is whether said the
nature the self is that it's not yours
it's not yourself so that's what needs
to be the stood on the basis of that
sense of self you have to stop denying
the sense of self because how can you
understand it if you're trying to give a
little bit if you're begin ordering it
if you're indulging arey
if you are basically engaging with it so
first you have to develop distraint
recognize that there is a sense of self
that is a problem because of which you
suffer so now within that sense of self
you want to see how that is not yours
mmm that's the understanding you pursue
so yes if you're doing it for those
reasons then you would be investigating
characteristics the signs and tokens is
the word I would say because they're
coming now against with like against the
background of the right context
is mmm investigation like is that no
never like is that the means which you
can develop an understanding but you
also have to understand that's not
completely understanding yeah that's the
closer to something that you can do in
order to develop understanding but if
you if you want to do rightly your
investigation must not lose the sight of
itself and by that I mean you should
already but I wanted to investigate you
should begin investigating why do you
want to investigate not like all the
investigation I found these random
things that the suitors talk what's all
investigated I'll ponder about it in
these like psychological terms now I
found these things I want to investigate
okay stop
why why do I want to investigate what is
the problem there must be a problem in
my experience as a whole that I'm trying
to overcome by practicing the Dhamma
by investigating by doing what this were
to say what is that problem so
investigation basically because starts
and it never really leaves the basis of
clarifying what the actual problem is
being very understanding what the
problem is will then get you to
understand what the solution is yeah
dukkha but again okay so what buddies do
content do I know I understood it for
you just any kind of genetic notion that
I sort of have concept of art okay okay
what is dukkha for me so understand that
and there you go through your
investigation look like investing in
your own motives you got to investigate
now the nature of the suffering and
that's certainly much closer to enabling
you to understand the nature of
suffering which is the first noble truth
this is suffering okay so you realize
then that people are not free from
suffering now because they haven't done
things rightly know
they simply don't understand even what
suffering is amidst of them suffering
they still don't understand what
suffering is but often people would
assume we kind of already simply by
suffering you know what suffering is and
now is just a question of performing a
set of prescribed rules and observances
and techniques and methods emotions and
you will then travel out of the of the
world of suffering know that that travel
begins by first actually understanding
that you don't know what suffering is
because the moment you understand what
suffering is you understand what they
were they escape from it is you
understand what the cause of it is you
won't be acting out of it well you
understand Four Noble Truths the only
reason you're acting out of it because
you're affected by and you're affected
by it because you don't understand
so that's another thing like you could
you arrived at oh so I want to present
my because suffering is the problem okay
so what would be the characteristics of
that suffering so you can take that in
various directions but for example now
as how we start to this you can answer
can you suffer without a sense of self
without any self awareness can you
experience dukkha if self awareness is
not there if there is no self awareness
awareness of this body and experience
yeah awareness of yourself recall any
suffering that you had mm-hmm did for
you would be the closest representative
of what you think Duke is is there a
perception of yourself there can you be
unaware of yourself while you're
suffering
you would be aware of yourself if there
was suffering yes so can you have
something without self-awareness can you
have feeling without self-awareness so
it's always a sense of self so you
feeling can be experienced but you
cannot have feel like would you think
like assuming feeling like feeling is
that toned the mood of your experiences
I mean of the experience is still there
but you do not assume that experience of
feel well then the feeling is not there
if you're not assuming it you can't have
two perspectives at once you're speaking
on is if you're both go to jail and had
another hunt and that doesn't work
you're either one end or the other so
you can't save your feeling but you're
not assuming the feeling for you the
only feeling you know is the feeling
that's being assumed don't the
aggregates continue to persist well how
would you know that
how can you see that for itself the only
way to see how can I gets possessed is
to become an adult which means your
current aggregates will not possess
because your cotton aggregates at top to
bottom affected by your piranha that's
what it would say matter would cease
feeling everything all the greed would
cease when you become enlightened
because when he speaks to petitioner
from this point of view yes everything
that he is assumed will cease to be so
but sure if you be step back from both
and assume the situation theoretically
yes aggregates persist but how to what
extent you can either continue thinking
it theoretically or recognize that that
situation does not apply to you thus
it's not accurate so for you feeling
perception and you agree that you know
is already assumed that's the whole
problem but to say that there is no more
accurate there is no more aggregate put that I
there is no more aggregate put that I
mean we cannot be denied okay Mike well
there's no more for the brothers still
no sense sure it's a it's a denial but
you denial is determined by your
motivation not by actually saying there
are no aggregates death is not to deny
up for another hunt cessation is not a
denial it's why you're doing the
cessation so if you're saying there are
no more aggregates there are no more
regulate could you basically just trying
to manage the pressure that current
assume aggregates are putting onto you
so you're just dismissing the problem
yeah then yeah that's a denial but it's
not the denial because of the dismissal
is now because of your intention behind
it I think it's why I may have read
often that there's the our hunt he's
awakened and he's developed the full
extent of knowledge but any there's
remainder there's still remainder left
yeah and that remainder left is the
aggregates yeah so see you got the idea
about it now and you have two options
you can either leave that idea as it is
and think it that it represents what our
hunt is oh you can then start
questioning that idea and say well if
you really understood another hunt you
would be at least a sort of honor so are
you sort of honor if the answer is no to
that means your idea of what ahadees is
not an accurate idea nobody denies that
there is an idea there but you mustn't
leave it for what it is because okay it
makes sense yeah but are you so depend
on account of that sense no means it's
not an accurate idea that's I mean you
have a degree of understanding but it's
because you don't push the understanding
that's why you don't get freedom from
suffering as a result of the
understanding it's not because you
haven't you know found all the right
understandings and so on or you haven't
been doing it long enough so you got the
idea about another hand but it cannot
accurately represent it because you're
still go to dinner
you cannot accurately represent this
so make more evident understand what
kind of what is the residue in the case
of an element and then if that
understanding frees you from suffering
you know you're on the right track
I suppose my understanding of the
aggregates I mean that would be
insufficient would you mean Mike Ike if
there's a conscious party the aggregates
must be there like that's let's see that
sort of you if there is a conscious body
aggregates must be there like experience
so how over experience
so again saying if there is a conscious
body occurrence must be there implies
that on account of your conscious body
you know the aggregates but conscious
body it's already where the aggregates
are there being a while so having a
conscious body means within that notion
of conscious body that you can relate to
that's where you decide the grades you
don't infer the aggregates on account of
having a conscious body thus the
aggregates must be there now having a
conscious body means the aggregates are
there as that conscious body so within
the basis within the context of
conscious body you can then discern more
of an aspect of material or emotional
over ever within the basis of conscious
body not kind of in response to
but if they're but again why would you
want to descend if I like it yes because
we're mentioning before I mean my
understanding isn't complete but there
was the idea that an hour hunt has no
more aggregates hmm fully enlightened
being doesn't experience aggregates
anymore so but for me currently I can't
understand how one can be alive or have
a living body and not experience it and
that's why you're still not another
finding out how is that possible
we'll make it least sort of fun but see
thinking that there is a thread that
unites you with a state of another hand
that you can think accurately is why
you're not understanding what another
one is because that thread stands in
place of what you think understanding of
another hand state is and that's often
people struggle with thinking that oh I
know I'm not so the pan-arab dujana
but my practice is helping me which
means I am somehow in some manner to
some extent on some level getting closer
to our country you don't have a clue
only sotapanna can know okay no now I
know exactly by the way is and I can
either pursue it or not but he knows so
unless there is a right view you should
not trust any understanding that you
have doesn't mean you should mystify to
pretend no it's just you know it's not
about understand it is about
understanding but it's about sufficient
understanding sufficient being at least
the understanding of the right of you
but see for as long as you think now did
your idea of other hand segregates is
accurate you're not gonna make effort to
understand how can I got under not heavy
could you think you figure it out and
now you're just about you know felling
watering doing this
doing that and somehow you get closer to
that that that state so yes from
petitioners point of view other hand has
no aggregates there's no being bhava he
sees he does not exist
it was the cessation of assuming sure
yes theoretically it is a cessation of
assuming but for you as we discussed
video that everything is true that
assuming so you can't think accurately
how would things be without assuming
because you're thinking that with your
assuming I thought that there would be
aggregates and no assuming that would be
empowered there would be a joints again
theoretically extrapolated from your
experience it doesn't apply to you so
that's not an accurate thought because
now any notion of aggregates you have
even arahants aggregates free from
assuming are your aggregates affected by
assuming so you can't have the accurate
thought of arahants aggregates while you
still go to dinner it's just impossible
because your thoughts are affected by
you're assuming thus anything within
those thoughts is equally affected by
assuming on your own a cessation of
feeling which is understood by someone
who sees the dummer yeah so the
cessation of feeling is the cessation of
that's not good sure sure waves decision
of wall exactly yeah but just just that
I'm just like if you
haven't got if you've got this idea of
the like yes advocates continue for the
what does that mean sensation feeling
Wow well he's alive you know that's just
well he's alive you know that's just
dumb just doesn't flag the hair that's
okay something no understood oh yeah but
the reason why people ignore the flags
is because it's quite frightening yeah
to now recognize that even the most
accurate ideas that you have about
Dhamma and instead of an are handed
everything you're still fully enclosed
within that sort of sinking ship of your
ignorance but if you actually are able
to accept that idea that's how you can
find a way out if you don't that will be
the reason why you want find a way out
doesn't matter how much other effort you
put in your practice
you see understanding is so enticing
because you know basically things make
sense yeah and that's exactly how it
should be think make sense but then you
question that extent of that sense you
made yeah hmm so okay so this makes
sense but am I free from suffering is
the last diminishing in me a version
desire for distraction are all these
things dissipating as a result of
understanding well then you should not
trust your understanding so said just
trusting about the fact that things make
sense yeah you have to okay that makes
sense let me see if I can make more
sense out of it and more sense and more
sense and more sense
and all of it converges on that Vayner
even this whole thing before you know
trying to understand the aggregates get
the idea of what outside gates are then
you know try and approximate it whatever
why because you don't want to suffer
which means you feel right here right
now your non freedom in regard to suffering
your non freedom in regard to suffering
you are still liable to it so then if
you stay within that context your
thinking will cease to be theoretical
because you still within the okay so
this is the measure this is the
container within which whatever I'm
trying to do or understand on account of
the Dhamma should be understood within
me being liable to so liability to
suffering what are the characteristics
how does that feel how would then
understanding of the aggregates free me
from this suffering but often people
start with yes of course I want to be
free from suffering then aggregates need
to be understood and then you go there
and completely forget and abandon the
context of why you're doing it in the
first place and that's how you become
you start thinking about the amount to
early abstract terms and then people
kind of understand oh well this is just
too abstract this doesn't really pertain
to suffering but then they will go too
far the other way oh just stop thinking
stop reading the suitor stop just sit
and meditate and your chitta will open
up and whatever else because they kind
of understood that this is abstract it
doesn't work but they haven't understood
that you can also learn how to think not
abstractly you can think on the basis on
the within the container of your feeling
and that motivation to be free from
suffering but that's a skill that needs
to be discerned right in the middle
there so it's usually either you
overthink it and becomes just abstract
and you divorce yourself which is the
definition of abstraction you divorce
yourself from that basis of feeling oh
then you just completely dismiss domain
of thinking which is ironically another
thought on account of which you just
start to mystify the present
here now judgment-free mind embodiment
and whatnot and then refused to think
refused to make the effort to understand
either way you failed to understand what
needs to be understood because you
overshot the mark then you under showed
it that may bring us back to the sense
of self bringing bringing the feeling
like you know well I think actually
that's probably even more accurate for
something what petitioner should do is
never lose the context of feeling
present enduring feeling within that you
wouldn't discern the signs of your mind
within that you will discern the signs
of yourself yeah off you sent yourself
off your sense of I am of your sense of
master controller within the feeling
you're subjected to
so then if you wanna choose a
contemplation so to speak in terms of
the suitors what needs to be understood
you choose the ones they will least
likely result in you distract being
distracted from what you're feeling
right there right there so don't think
about the third jhana and relationship
to the base of nothingness cuz you're
still a potted unit doesn't even know
them doesn't even have a Monday in the
right view and yet here you I want to
understand all this it John is make
again understand in other words you're
just acting out of craving to have
things laid out figured out in a sense
that you want them to be you know
putting your finger on to it
it's basically always rooted in craving
even on the mental level so why do I
won't understand five and a half Janice
oh because I want practice but why do I
wanna practice Buddhist teaching cuz I'm
worried from suffering with suffering
and suffering right now no but I am
liable to suffer oh so it's right here
right now my ability to suffering it's
always present I'm always within it it's
always my reality and on account of that
I'll forget about it and they're not
going to figure these random things Rd
then I read a lot of failures it doesn't
work it's just thinking so when I can't
do want you to be free from suffering I
will abandon that awareness of that
liability in order to dismiss the
thinking and then mystified my present
moment either way he basically concealed
the problem although you started with
the problem with the recognition of it
so that's what me the idea you have of
the father five aggregates of another
hunt habitant you think about it and
also allow your liability to suffering
to be there discerned so is your idea
freeing you from that liability means
it's not if you're doubtful about it
it's not freeing you from it it's not
clear thus it cannot be magically
freeing you from it unless you
know it so then take that development
idea further until it fully binds in
connects goes right through the center
of that liability to suffering
so their liability to suffering is that
mmm it's wanting a feeling it's tell you
what I wanted no no no just well Jesus
felt being within fuel you can try and
define it all you want they will all be
secondary to the fact that it's felt and
how is it felt and that's the definition
of dukkha which really means this is so
crazy Duke Lee's opportunities and that's the
Duke Lee's opportunities and that's the
thing so you know you don't need to
suffer right here right now in terms of
something really affecting you a mere
recognition that you are liable to
suffer and you cannot even fathom how
could you defend yourself from it you
have no access to that exposure to
suffering you just recognize it that is
so that's Duke and then that Duke is the
chief of all the Duke all other
suffering experience has to come within
the basis of that liability to suffering
that liability of feeling it's like like
how that once with this says like even
in pleasant feeling it's named for
seeing it as painful yeah exactly a
handful yeah
yeah you you're liable you're liable to
suffer advanced means any any feeling
any change in the feeling can be that
suffering which means any feeling is
that suffering could you liable to feel
it can you be liable to suffering if you
don't feel anything
impossible so liability to suffering for
you means liability to feeling so that's
why if you cherish entertain welcome
delighting act out of feeling that you
want makes you equally than liable to
feelings that you don't want because you
can't just have half of the feelings and
not the other half impossible the only
way to free yourself from liability
suffering is to free yourself from
liability to feeling and you free
yourself from liability feeling by you
know being restrained not acting out of
the feelings and then understanding the
nature and arisen feeling whatever that
feeling is
and once you see that that involves the
fact that old feelings come before any
sense of self yeah yeah you don't even
have to think about sense of self in
this particularly God if you just
recognize the liability of feeling
enduring oh I feel okay now but I'm not
saying it thus I will not have saying
when there changes and you will have to
change one way or the other
and what if you change for words exactly
what if you change for better
exactly you've no control either way you
were subjected to it so how can you free
yourself from something you've no
control over
firstly by understanding what why is it
I provide why there is a problem with it
there is a problem with it sometimes
people tell well ok it's just so the
feeling is just on the other hand can
say that but we don't start as our hands
we started petunias thus your feeling is
just so means my feeling is just so and
it's a problem for being you just so-so
you don't know mystified but you
certainly don't abstract yourself from
it either so not being in control of
your feelings why is it a problem I can
I'm affected I could be affected at any
time and even when I have a pleasant
feeling arise it's lonely glass a
certain period of time I walk more of it
and I can't get more of it well then I
suffer on account of that so because of
the problem is the problem of not being
control feeling is because you'll be
affected why is that a problem while
being affected by feeling is a problem
being affected is it's painful
yes I can't I can't so use that sound
okay so that's even more accurate being
affected it's painful wise pain
it's a problem
why is pain
it is a problem of why why is the
problems
sometimes I mean I guess I'm thinking of
degrees of pain but that's not the same
yeah we don't know the pain no matter
what agree
why is paying a problem
being affected by it and that's why I
can them I'm yeah I'm exposed I'm
vulnerable I'm susceptible to it that's
all that is a problem because it's
painful being exposed vulnerable
susceptible what they all have in common
is that they are uncomfortable
discomfort means pain so we're back on
to wise pain the problem and the pain is
a problem always and only for one reason
it's because you want to get rid of it
so the pain is not a problem problem is
not in the pain problem is in you always
automatically not wanting get so that's
what the problem is your attitude so can
you be susceptible to something without
that being painful would you would being
susceptible to something be a problem if
it's not painful no and then would
something be painful if you're not
trying to get rid of it if you're not
craving against it no so then the
problem is your craving not the pain not
the lack of control not being
susceptible not being liable none of
these things are a problem the problem
is your craving of not wanting it so
when non control is a problem it's only
so because you still crave control and
that's why they would like the
mindfulness recollectionist of death is
like a direct the quickest the sharpest
way as well towards a Timeship literally
have a thought of dying the next moment
next in-breath are you affected by if
you are it's not because of death or
anything that can befall you it's
because you resisting to accept it
resisting craving against it
and that's why again the first noble
truth understanding what suffering is
this is what's up that's that's this is
that understanding you really suffering
is not in the pain pain is not suffering
but for petitioner for another light in
mind there is no pain without suffering
because there is no pain without craving
against the pain but the suffering is in
the craving why because if suffering
were in the pain the removal of pain
would mean removal of suffering but it's
not
but if suffering is in the craving if
you remove the craving yeah you have
pain in because you don't always suffer
when you experience pain by the way if I
tell you oh if you endure some matter no
physical discomfort for ten minutes and
then you'll be rewarded by sixty billion
dollars and in a life of luxury and and
you never have to work a day in your
life that pain will be joyful for you
because you know what's at the end of it
all is the Buddha would say if you
practice you the pain of restrain you'll
be rewarded with the can and the rivers
life's of luxury and any enjoy then that
pain but if the pain is always suffering
you would suffer you would not accept
that deal because pain is always
suffering but it isn't and every time
you go to work we have to hold you do to
you that's so painful that's so
uncomfortable but you don't resist it
because you have a bigger picture in
your mind that this contributes towards
that bigger picture which is picture of
pleasure even being even wanting the
freedom from suffering is the picture of
pleasure and that's just a natural
principle that's how it works
so suffering is not in the pain because
if it were so there would be no self
awareness of it whenever there is pain
there suffering I'm stupid absence of
suffering absence of liability to suffer
as well and you would not have a
recognition of it but the fact is that
suffering is in your craving towards
pain see if I tell you if you do this
pain for 10 minutes and then you have a
exponential reward you won't claim
against the pain you will want that pain
cuz you want the reward
and you won't suffer in regard to the
pain although you would suffer if I tell
you I just tricked you I'm not giving
you the reward and without inflicting
any physical pain on you and you would
suffer on account of it more than you
suffer on physical pain being inflicted
upon you why because you're craving
determines the suffering first you were
not craving against it you are not
claiming against the pain but you were
very much Crapo the great reward
so craving is present in regards to the
reward I tell you there is no reward
your cravings there you suffer because
of a craving you want to protect your
reward because of your craving you want
to defend it you will cry on account of
it if you lose it because of the craving
so pain is the problem because of your
craving with us pain is not a problem
your craving is a problem but saying
that now for somebody who is not free
from craving saying ok so pain is not a
problem well that's an idea but if that
idea is not freeing you from suffering
as in not freeing you from craving means
pain is the problem for you because you
don't know how not to cream in regard to
the pain so that's I mean sometimes
people get a hint that Oh suffering is
not in the pain but then overly accept
any feeling that comes their way
ok so this is just so there is no
problem in this just accept it just let
it go can you let go of you or your idea
of letting go can you really let go of
that can see I'm letting go of all of
this it still allows me to have at least
some sense of control I'm just
practicing letting go a sense of control
is sense of craving so you letting go of
your cravings with your craving and
usually those people get very upset if
if that view is challenged they might
not get upset on account of things
they're letting go but if the view of
that letting go is challenged
they get upset they defend it because
they have using their control and on
account of it they suffer so it's not an
accurate application of your effort in
other words you want to apply your
effort whereby what you are letting go
is resulting in freedom from suffering
in every regard
now just in this particular little
corner it works but if anything else
changes if if somebody challenges it
I'll be affected I'll be emotionally
disturbed on account of it
so how would you not create for pain
that's what my ability to pain is that's
well ability the suffering is
its inability to not crave just think of
a stock answer yeah craving yeah so
craving is not a matter of choice but at
the same time is something you're
responsible for as long as a non are
hard I'm responsible for craving yeah
and when it arises well on it
you've never freed from craving because
you always feel something which means
you always crave something and you got
the feeling
that's why craving is not in regard to
only regard to pain it's in regard to
the domain of whatever's felt so if you
feel Pleasant you will automatically
crave towards it if you feel unpleasant
you will automatically crave away from
it if you feel neither well you will
automatically create towards distracting
yourself from it so how can you stop
that automatic craving because you are
responsible for it craving is not part
of the aggregate it's not part of the
things that arise for you it's your
attitude towards it stopping refusing
did stopping the denial of feeling and
stopping the giving into it
but why would you want to stop the
denial of feeling what would be your
motivation behind that no longer be
effective the craving to denied you want
to stop the denial you wanted to stop
the noun is rooted in denying the
craving because how are you affected by
craving as I said claiming doesn't arise
in the same sense feelings arise for you
so what is there to stop
do you ever notice well your your
understand your attitude towards it
so I was thinking towards what to look
towards the order is what I was thinking
God so let's let's stick with the
feeling and craving that's what I mean
so so you can't attend you to craving
claiming is not an object of your mind
oh I see my craving but for as long as
you think that you can convey me is
peripheral in regard to whatever's
presently felt yeah for as long as you
keep the understanding that you can
affect the feeling you can change it you
you have a right to know want this
feeling to be there right yeah good cuz
it's two different things by the way you
can't change your feeling I mean
sensuality has effect yeah it will has
effect yeah oh my god it's completely
has nothing to do with anything it works
yeah it's the only way that petitioner
knows of working yeah but the thing you
refer to is like you have a right to do
so that's a different thing and that's
already do the level of the view yeah I
have a right to interfere with this
feeling which means I have a right to
claim against the feeling for the
feeling and for as long as you don't
abandon the view that you have a right
to do so you will be automatically doing
it so so only through going against the
grain of that view that I have a right
you will stop doing it and that's how
you stop that automatic response of
craving by ceasing to provide
maintenance for it and this view that
you have a right to do so is how you
maintain the attitude of claiming of
doing so
so abandon the view that you have a
right towards pleasurable feeling
towards unpleasant feeling towards the
into feeling you don't have a right
which ever feeling is there you
subjected to it you have no rights over
it you within it yo the other self wanna
say you
what kind of subordinate and that cannot
change any change that you can inflict
so to speak is within it with its engine
which fully contains you that you have
to do so stop giving in to the means of
changing feeling on account of what's
felt that's how you will stop
perpetuating craving understand and
that's not something off here is a
recipe just stick to these rules and
these methods because different
literally different whenever you become
recollect of the present moment there is
a feeling and during their which means
they're going to be an attitude towards
it and that's the attitude you need to
be dealing with not the theory of the
attitude that I must do so what are you
feeling right here right now neutral
what is are you are you aware of it are
you losing the sight of that neutral are
you being distracted towards other
things that's your work then I feel
unpleasant is there an implicit attitude that I
is there an implicit attitude that I
should not feel this I have a right to
not feel this I'm entitled to not feel
this I can't wait for it to go away all
these thoughts are exemplification of
the attitude that I am first and this
just here temporarily amongst even I
will endure it for the rest of my life
why oh because I don't want it to be
here it's that so what you do not count
of it it's whether you feel exactly why
why are you doing it which will reveal
whether you feel entitled and you will
for as long as you're not aware of it so
you can act it on a counterfeit but
disappearance between acting on account
of it with the thought that under the
impression that I am in control of it
and under the impression that I'm not in
control like I did I it's not my right
well to me it bends what what acting on
economy means and it's skillfully not
like it it's not against the precepts
not against the training right yeah well
that's the thing if it's if it's not
against the precept if it's nothing
straining you're not really acting out
of it anything a lead means acting for
the purpose of either getting more of
this feeling or getting rid of this
feeling but that only applies on the
life of the body and that's not what the
feeling is rooted so you have to start
by not acting out of it as in not going
against the presets but then see it's
not against the precepts to go alone and
sit be alone in you could sit quietly so
it's not on the level of unwholesomeness
of breaking the presets but you might be
one doing it for very unwholesome
reasons so you can't just say oh it's
just a question of not acting out of it
not acting out of it first to contain
yourself well then it's a question of
understanding whatever current feeling
whatever Cardon feeling is and whatever your
Cardon feeling is and whatever your
attitude towards it is so you might be
on paper wholesome cause you're always
secluded in your couch and so on but the
true reason for there might because you
hate everybody else you can't stand
other people everything is a disturbance
so you just want to find the environment
that's in your control my cooter if
somebody comes and tells you get out of
there Cody would you remain indifferent
and economist or would you be disturbed
so what you need to do is know the
motivation in regard to present
hindering feeling and not lose the sight
of it
because that's what acting out truly is
you know in ignoring that degree of that
motivation behind cuz I said oh I will
not act out of my feeling y ou cuz I
want to get rid of it so now for me
getting rid of the feeling is abstaining
from getting rid of the feeling and you
can never okay always look at your
motivation that's your methods yeah I
suppose you can say that but why do I
want to do that exactly so why am i
doing that
which means always has to be discerned
on the on the on the basis of a
recollected present experience as a
whole because that's where the
motivation is that's what the feeling is
induced that's where the moods are so
now while you're trying to figure out
what I'm saying why ask yourself okay so
why is this important to be understood
and that's how you'll understand what
I'm saying to be free from suffering to
be free from yes so why do you want to
be free from suffering now is it because
they thought it implies you're not free
not free so how does that implication
manifest in your experience do you not
free from suffering how's that because
feeling is felt yes so how is that it
I'm not free from suffering is that a
concern for you he's concerned
unpleasant yes is this pleasure
the problem is pain a problem so through
going through this basically almost like
drills of reflection you keep happening
in the context that pain Volunteers of
feeling valid induced it's not a problem
but there is no problem without the
feeling and that's how you get to then
discern the attitude peripherally to the
problem of the field
and they're so good Ahmet Hooper done is
not in the final days but there is no
Padano without the family it's being
there but usually people think about
holding an attachment what everyone has
translated it just becomes another thing
another thing I can attend to focus on
say no to choose it no you can do that
with things that aggregates present you
but you put on is not in them nobody
nothing nothing between nothing responds
nothing yet without aggregates there is
no putana but if you look at the
aggregates you're not gonna see you
putana it's completely peripheral from
you look off the aggregates same with
the feeling there's something that you
can't see you're craving you can't say
no to your craving because that's not
craving you claiming that craving is
peripheral to present enduring feeling
so discern recollect present enduring
feeling as I said oh well suffering is
not being control is a problem I will
cause cause I'm liable to it it implies
I can suffer Oh how's that although
that's felt as a concern what is a
concern a concern is unpleasant feeling
didn't yours
so I'm craving against it I wouldn't
have a problem with concern if by some
whatever reason it's not felt
unpleasantly any problem you have in the
world any problem you had you would have
you will have it's only problem for one
reason it's felt unpleasantly and not
not crave against it
so concerned is not a problem anxiety is
not a problem none of these things that
are problem hey is the problem because
you cannot you don't know how not to
create for it
know is just symptoms those are just
further results and then we reverse the
pain is on the problem either
it's my craving that's the problem
that's why I suffer that's what I said
presence of clearly means presence of
suffering absolutely absence of
suffering and that's simultaneous so
whenever there is a suffering present in
me means craving is present in me to the
extent the very suffering whenever there
is no suffering present in me then there
is no craving present in me are usually
people regarded in the linear sense of
craving is a matter of choice you just
say no - it's a note it and somehow down
the line your feelings will wither away
and then and then you'll be free from
everything no could you claim for that
because you're not aware of your
motivation in regard to why you're doing
it in the first place like when I asked
you the other day in the talk are you
liable to suffering yeah why is that a
problem how does that feel right here right now
how does that feel right here right now
so if you don't feel suffering on
account of right here right now
liability to suffering would you then
suffering kind of anything that can
comes in there liability impossible
because you approach to the feeling the
recognition of my suffering but the only
reason this is a problem is because I
don't know this caper of suffering which
is another way of saying I don't know
how to stop claiming that's when the
Four Noble Truths is once you understand
what the true problem is which is not
the pain it's the claiming in the God
are that's where the problem is you
don't understand that absence of that
means absence of the problem regardless
even if the people come and you know
start shopping your lives in a
and everything else you will not suffer
because suffering was never in those
things suffering is not in the aggregate
in the same sense super than is not in
the aggregate
it can even ask you sir why is that why
is the why is the pain of interrogation
unpleasant cuz you came against the pain
of it because you crave against the pain
of it so it's suffering because you
crave against it well because in itself
it's suffering I guess then there's
what's the motivation of knowing that
it's painful but the pleasure derived I
guess no you have to stop like that
that's what we lament the what was it
can see these the cravings to be banned
with means of craving conceived by the
means of conceit so you crave now to be
free from craving as a result of that
craving you will hopefully do the right
let's understand the right things make
the right effort they will result in
cancelling that very crazy
and what is that what I'm describing so
because you want to be free from
suffering you start to question the
nature of the feeling and then you get
to realize that suffering is not in the
feeling it's in the attitude in regard
to that feeling and then you get to
realize the data it should is not a
matter of your choice but more like a
matter of your secondary choices the
result in feeding their attitude choices
towards pleasure choices to is no pain
acting out of it so you stop doing that
and you stop feeling the suffering feed
in the craving sorry and that's how you
destroy the craving on account of the
very creamy filling the craving is
reading the sufferer yeah of course
that's very synonymous
craving enduring presence of craving
peripherally as the attitude of your
mind is felt as suffering it's the same
thing now if I got there screaming and
they did it suffering there's one thing
edge to the craving that's felt
suffering so removing that you're
craving cannot anymore result in feeling
suffering but the reason see it's so
hard well it's so easy because the attitude
well it's so easy because the attitude
is invisible as I said you can't attend
to your craving you can't see oh this is
my craving you only feel suffering and
then when you look all you sees things
in front of you I see this I see that
thus natural response response with the
grain of death deception is I suffer
because he said that I suffer because I
lost this there is losing of this and
suffering simultaneously present but
it's a mistake of the like fundamental
proportion to assume that because
they're simultaneous present that's why
this is suffering and that's the nature
of ignorance that's why when a region
cannot be in the aggregates cannot be in
things you perceive or feel or intend
it's in regard but it cannot be found
anywhere else except for those things up
because how can you mistake your
suffering for something you perceived or
even for the feeling you felt if feeling
and perception were not there is nothing
to be mistaken with